wait what just happened are we recording
is this thing on okay we're going to
talk about something very dangerous uh
it's one of the most dangerous times in
your career in my opinion and uh I'm
going to tell you a story I'm going to
tell you a story about how this happened
to me and how I discovered it back in
the 90s and the and and it's going to
just bear with me okay so back in the
90s uh I was you know Nikes Web Master a
lot of you know that and um thank you
for the hats up and I I mean I got an
award one of the few coveted Awards um
you know that there is a finished L for
building their swoosh net their internal
Network and everything the reason you
need to know that is because around that
time um I was also giving a lot of
presentations you know convention
presentations and um my skills were at
the top of my game I was at the top of
my game my skills were really good IID
really built them up a lot I'd spent a
lot of private time building my skill
set and maybe this sounds like you right
so you you've dedicated a lot of time
built this amazing skill set and now
people are starting to take notice of
you and this is when the danger comes so
what happened was because I
had uh developed this reputation and and
and all these skills and was giving
regular presentations and everything um
I started getting away from the tech
that made me that gave me the
reputation and so the thing that I had a
reputation for was knowing knowing what
was emerging knowing what was good
knowing how to do it learning it really
quickly being able to dissect it and
research it understand it and then put
it into terms that people could
understand these are all you know skill
sets that I that I have and knowing your
own skill set is sort of a separate
topic but the point is that I was not
doing the thing that gave me the
reputation and somebody in the chat was
was talking about this they're they're
they're at this place in life where they
are now uh you know they're a manager so
kind of fast forward my situation the
story I'm telling you about they are a
manager and they they're over five or
six people and they're in meetings all
the time and they're dealing with
support tickets and they're in in
meetings they're not they're hands
they're completely separated from the
technology now I I call that I don't
know what a better term for this is but
I have often called this manager suck
and the reason I call it suck it's not
because management sucks I didn't even
spell it right
management do I have to remake this
video because I spelled it wrong okay
I'm leaving it on because with the
misspelling I typed it really fast
management maybe this is why I like
never got any real jobs I put it like I
am I putting this this is my new way of
spilling
management just like
strimmer I'm not a smart man okay let me
finish my story I'm going to finish my
St
because I make videos quickly so you
have videos otherwise I don't make
videos so so beware beware of the mag
man
manag dub sucks creating new Enterprise
yeah why not okay so let me finish my
story I am not getting rid of this video
you can make fun of me for not knowing
how to spell all you want I'll let it
I'm going to leave it I'm going to leave
it because I I suck I did this
quickly you should not listen to me you
really shouldn't but but I'm giving you
at least one perspective okay anyway
so that is so pathetic I can't stand
it um I'm pathetic anyway so this
pathetic guy was all of a sudden getting
asked to go raw is better all right well
Ro so this pathetic guy was all of a
sudden a subject matter expert and I was
getting called into all these meetings
all the time and guess what other people
on my team were stepping in to do the
fun stuff they were doing the tech they
were installing the software they were
writing the software they were they were
playing around with Hardware they were
dealing with Linux they were the ones
having all the fun and I was getting
pulled in these really boring ass
meetings where that were fun at first at
first the meetings were really fun right
because they were like massaging my ego
and making me feel important and like oh
my God we got it we got Rob here we're
super happy to have our subject matter
esper and recently Award winner you know
like
yeah you know I I it was for all the
wrong reasons I was going to these
meetings you know and and and yeah I
mean everybody's vulnerable to this
right we we like being um you know the
best at something and I was okay no
cursing I promise and so I mean I I
definitely
was I definitely was was the best at
that stuff right well so I don't you
probably guess where this story is going
so the more I got pulled into these
meetings I got sucked into these
meetings see that's where the word comes
from the more I got sucked into these
meetings for being such a great you know
subject matter expert on this particular
topic and blah blah blah blah blah
talking about how to do things and and
make helping them make you know
Intelligent Decisions about the things
you know blah blah blah blah blah blah
blah the more I got talking to it the
less I typing I was doing I wasn't doing
any typing I was just blah blah
bling the ironic thing is that my I my I
didn't start making any more money I
just felt more important and this is the
danger my friends this is the
this is the danger the danger is
this getting pulled away from your skill
SE stack stack I can't talk I knock my
teeth
out getting pulled away from the thing
that makes you great your technology
skills your engineering skills your
whatever their core skills are getting
pulled away from those things so that
you can help other people succeed by
giving your expertise to them for free
in meetings without them paying you anym
and taking you away from the ability to
keep your skills up and learning them is
a very dangerous place to be it's a very
dangerous place to be you need to make a
decision and some of you watching this
video are probably there right now you
are you you can feel that you are not
good with your technology you're you're
you're no longer the best at any of the
things that got you the job or the award
right you have become you know sort of
stale and if you're in technology this
can take like a month you can become
stale that because stuff moves so
quickly right so four meetings in that
month are going to make you more stale
than the person who's a junior who's
who's probably making less than you but
they're doing more than you and their
skill set is rising fast and we're going
to we're going to we're going to come
back to this because uh you're there
currently right so so if you
are but I just I just want to tell you
this is a super dangerous time for you
because because this is what happens
right some hungry Junior engineer and
there's actually another story there's
another target audience
here the other target audience is the
hungry ass junior junior Engineers who
are motivated who are getting told
there's no jobs for junior Engineers
today now is your opportunity to strike
if you if if if you have a a tech lead
who is really egotistical like I kind of
was for that time and getting pulled
into these meetings they're vulnerable
and you should strike that's when you
strike that's when you shine that's when
you study you you don't even go to the
meeting no that's your job you need to
go to the tech meeting yeah oh thank you
for going to those Tech meetings and you
[__] sorry I'm swearing you like
learn everything you learn all the
things you start quietly saying oh I can
help you out with that you start taking
over you start Shadow taking over all of
the work of that person you push them
out of that job now usually there's
enough work to go around they're not
going to get pushed out but what that
now you're shining because now you're
cheaper and you're doing the same thing
that other person was do and then you
push that other person to make a
decision
that other person that other person
either has to come back and
say that other person either has to come
back and say scoot over that's my
project which they will
do which is very
unpopular right and they'll say no get
out of go that's my thing don't do it
now look I'm not I'm not telling you to
be you know a technocrat I'm not telling
you to own the technocrat but there are
there are dynamics in in the workplace
and I'm just telling you this is how it
ends up going down right so the person
so we're talking to two people here
we're talking to the hungry hungry
Junior engineer and to the engineer who
has let themselves be sucked away from
the tech they are sucked completely away
from the technology they've been
flattered to death they're in all these
meetings they have no skills anymore
their skills are completely soft they
couldn't even do the thing that they
basic things anymore you know it you
know it you feel it right and unless
they've got a home lab and they're
trying to keep up Tech technology bisi
and and they're also not getting paid
more so let me talk let me talk to that
person I'm going talk to that person
first you need to make a decision and
pardon my French but [__] or get off the
pot you either have to go full-blown
manager which is going to make more
money and it's going to be more Prestige
and you're going to be asked to give
more conference talks and you're going
to you're going to you're seriously it's
going to be really great for your
ego but it might be really really bad
for your job security
why who are the first people to get
cut who are the first people to get cut
when the when the economy turns
down there are the smmes who have moved
over into management who are not high
enough in management to be able to
protect
themselves they're not they're not high
enough in management to protect
themselves so when it when a you know a
cost savings event
happens they just look at the they look
at all the people that are making all
the money and they look at middle
managers that's what you've just become
and now you are a Target Don Tapscott
who wrote uh the web generation back in
the 90s I actually met him and he said
and I sat I sat in one of his meetings
and I'm so glad that I sat in that
meeting I sat in the meeting and he said
he said if you have middle in your name
change jobs now and and his whole take
which turned out to be completely true
was that the web
particularly at the time this was in the
90s that the web was going to remove all
of the middle layers from everything
just look at Amazon now the entire
retail Market of our world is collapsing
because everybody can buy something
directly from Amazon or Alibaba or
wherever the [__] the point is if you
have middle manager in your name in your
title your head is on The Chopping Block
because more and more people are going
to be able to to and now that we have ai
you know more and more people are going
to be able to the people who need a
thing who have the money can now you
know employ people who can make the
thing more directly and they don't need
those middle managers as much as much so
so to the person who is in the
management position who has decided to
go into management to Tech management
team leads uh you know minor tech leads
project managers project managers are a
little bit of a different thing because
they're not really necessarily Technical
and they're usually delivering on
projects which does does still keep them
employed because they are still
producing value but the people that are
doing those middle management think
those people are in in in great danger
uh particularly if you've been told that
you're a tech lead and you're getting
pulled away from the away from the tech
so when I when I when I say if just be
aware of it right I if if you want to go
over there um so what happened to me I
had to make a decision right and um my
decision was to start fighting back and
I um I said no I'm not going to these
meetings anymore and I used to start I
very simply I started turning down
meetings I did I started turning down
meetings I turn it I turned down uh PMS
are useless yeah um well the reason you
think they're useless is exactly what
Tom Tapscott was talking about you don't
think they're necessary because you can
take the stakeholders and have them talk
directly to people doing the work right
and that that is that is something
that's something of a modern phenomenon
and and I agree with that anyway so so
when you consider all of these factors
and my decision at the time this was 90
eight uh was to say no to say no I I
want to stay an engineer uh I want to
stay a tech I actually had a
conversation with my manager I loved her
to death she was amazing and she was
like okay and so they C they stopped
calling me they stopped bringing me in I
would still go out as a as a kind of a
business systems analyst and and help
people you know come to swiet and know
why they wanted I had to still Market uh
our services uh but I could do that from
and still keep my tech skills fresh and
and I did I I spent a lot of time doing
doing that um and and it worked out well
um until uh I started to have tension
with some of the people on our team uh
which for many reasons not all
necessarily based on the fact that I was
doing more of these things um but and
you know that that uh that eventually
led to me moving to a different team and
working on that team and having to De
with the same sort of thing and but that
time but then I had the opposite problem
then they literally lock walked us in
our cubicles when they were doing Nike
ID and for we were working 90 hours a
week and they were destroying me uh so
much so that my my my wife at the time
had a panic attack and she came in and
she screamed at all of them on a random
Sunday when they told me I had to come
in uh and and I I said I was done and
the next day I I was going to quit it
brought me in to talk to the manager the
manager said we understand that you need
a new transmission in your car because
my wife had screamed at top of her lungs
the day before and they said we want to
pay for that
so the the moral of this story is uh
ultimately they were working me too hard
because I was doing the technology I was
doing I was good and I was an engineer
and I decided I didn't want to be a
manager uh which meant that I they were
overworking me because I was an
engineer even though I could walk uh
they put us all in a room said hey we
know it's hard but it's Doom environment
uh half the people quit the next day one
of the people that quit gave his gave my
name to their recruiter recruiter called
me said I don't have time to talk to you
unless you can double myself salary says
no problem can be in Dallas I said I
flew to Dallas they doubled my salary
and I got a job for IBM doing the same
thing doing technical things just in a
different
area but I was able to move around I had
the flexibility to move and leave and
everything because why because I had a
sharp skill set I had kept my tools
sharp and my personal take on this I I I
I think manager skills are absolutely
amazing the first month I did uh
training at IBM they told me we had a
thing where we had had to do something
outside of your comfort zone and they
had me be a manager for the for the team
or mock team and they said man you're
good at this you should do this and I
was like yeah I guess I could have done
it but but I I don't like it because it
makes me
uncomfortable because I there's always
going to be people that are going to
need go skills they're going to need
kubernetes they're going to need Linux
there's people that are always going to
need those things and people that have
money need those skills they're always
going to have those they're going to
need those skills you keep good with
those skills and you you know I call
them [__] you skills because you can
leave instantly and go get a job
someplace else at any time at any time
in fact so much so people become
extremely arrogant who stay Engineers a
lot of them to the point where it kind
of gets there's lots of there's lots of
videos on YouTube about memes about this
so by staying an engineer you're going
to get overworked uh you're not going to
get paid as much uh but when you know
stuff hits the fan you're going to be
able to pick up and walk because you're
going to have those skills that allow
you to move and go anywhere you want
that flexibility
uh and sustainability and that the
feeling inside that I don't ever have to
be afraid of a job uh you yeah it's it's
the the feeling of absolute peace that I
know that if if I got fired today I
could have a job within a month knowing
that my skills are sharp it's a very
amazing feeling you do not have that
feeling if you're getting sucked by
management into meetings and your skills
are getting
soft you don't have the the guarantee
from the company that you're putting
your trust in to give away your
knowledge you're giving away your
knowledge to all these people in the
room and they're not paying you any more
money and you don't have any more job
security is it worth
it you decide I I don't think it is I
don't think it is I would I would rather
be the and this this it sounds like a
flex but I I have been on many teams I
have been the lead I've been the lead
but I was never lead in title because
people knew that they could come to Rob
and ask me any question and I would help
them out and I was okay with doing that
and I didn't hoard my skills I was
actually given a thanks award at IBM uh
by several of my colleagues because I
was so open with my skills and I was so
dedicated to keeping my Linux skills up
like when we set up the DNS server and I
taught one of my uh Army he he was an
army guy and he came in he knew slur but
he didn't know Linux I taught him Linux
and so you know I I this is this is the
true definition of ocracy when you when
your skills are so good that you lead
automatically you just lead when you're
in the room they know my wife my wife is
the same same sort of person she's just
that kind of way with art and it and
she's just Rising like crazy really
quickly in in her world because because
her sense of of of presence is is is
just felt because she's just so capable
right I would rather be highly capable
and paid modestly
then overworked and or or or not as
capable and you know involved in a lot
of this meeting even though I'm a live
streamer so I don't know don't trust
your employers yeah million dollar
advice received at no cost um
so this is this maybe this will help you
navigate the tech world as I said I want
to speak a little bit to the junior
again um I am swimming
yes I'm swimming I'm swimming right here
so a little bit of advice to the to the
to the Juniors again um and again number
one piece of advice don't call yourself
a junior stop it you're not a junior
you're a programmer you're an engineer
stop calling yourself a junior okay just
stop and I've done this video before
stop stop calling yourself a junior
you're an engineer if if you need to
quantify it say how much experience you
have in terms of of of time and projects
but don't call yourself an engineer
don't just don't do it stop it
and um this is your time to
strike
okay so your your time your time to
strike is literally when you see other
people getting pulled into
meetings and I'm not tell I'm not
telling you to aggressively when I say
strike I it kind of sounds like you're
you know a jerk and I'm not saying be a
jerk about it but what I'm saying
is let's do it in a different way your
opport to shine and have people notice
you is when your team lead or your is
getting pulled into meetings and
something like that you can take on
these and and not only that but you're
going to you're going to start building
a relationship with a person who's
getting pulled into these meetings and
as long as you don't burn that bridge by
saying no you can't work on that's my
project now when they want to come back
it's like you know you're kind of
lifting you're lifting them up at the
same time um another opportunity for
engineers for junior Engineers actually
there was a guy
that I used to know I used to hang out
with uh in Oregon I won't say where but
um he was a senior engineer and his um
he used to call himself the pocket
engineer for the
CTO so this is another piece of advice
for people going into tech one of the
highest paying positions is you guys
play anybody play Team pches 2 you know
how you have a pocket medic you're like
the heavy you're like the heavy right
but you got a pocket medic it's keeping
you
alive um having a pocket engineer a CTO
they tried to make me by the way there
the the the the what was it uh the
distinguished engineer uh in Toronto
when I changed over they on paper they
gave me the software title finally even
though I was doing it for like five
years it was great I got raised
automatically and anyway they um this
distinguished engineer who had totally
her skills were soft and she knew knew
it she knew it I got to be careful how I
talk about this cuz she might watch
someday um she knew her skills were soft
and she brought me she flew me into
Toronto from Oregon because she they
wanted me or or Arizona I can't remember
they needed me on this project they
needed me to consult with them because
they had just bought internally they had
consumed our project that had completely
embarrassed the entire tily project line
uh because it was
better that that actually happened I can
provide references for that and and
yeah to we Global Services was selling
our stuff as a thing and their customers
were saying you need to go don't you
have another product that does that that
Sil we sells and they're like oh and
then it became this huge thing and they
consumed us and I had to go so I'm in
there at the first time I was ever
officially in a and this this this this
highly highly paid um very very soft uh
distinguished engineer was in there and
she identified me really quickly as
the because I had kept my you know and
she came up to me many many times during
the whole thing and I could tell she was
courting me to be her pocket
engineer and this is a thing this is a
thing so there are a lot of times there
are people that get that decide to go
the management route and they're they
know that they cannot survive they they
don't even have time to research the
technology to know decision the
important decisions they have to make
this happened I became the pocket
engineer for the director of technology
for several colleges in the area just
because I was mentoring their kids kids
there was a vice president for a very
very big corporation that you would know
who I is still on my Facebook she
actually went Point offered me a quar
million dollar job because she would sit
with with me for 20 minutes after
because she wanted the expertise she
wanted the this is not me bragging this
is me telling you a scenario that you
might consider and that is by staying
sharp you might become the pocket
engineer for one of these and because
these Executives have to they have to
stay on on top of this stuff and they
can't do it and you've already said
you're going to stay the best possible
technologist there is on that particular
thing and so these these CTO the people
that that rise to the highest levels of
top the people the people who rise to
the highest levels of management in in
it the way they do it the way they do it
is they identify one or two pocket
Engineers who are on paper aren't even
associated with them they're not on
their team they're they're they just
what they do is they build this thing
you've lived in someone's pocket yeah
yeah and and they so but this guy I was
telling you about that was his situation
too the per he was he was he was doing
very well and he had you absolute job
security no matter what and he was paid
very well he's paying much more than the
average person in his field because he
was the CTO pocket engineer in the C's
like I am not letting this person
go and I don't even know a pocket
engineer as a term that's something I
say uh maybe I coined it I don't know
but but you can be somebody's pocket
engineer and you can make them shine if
you're okay with giving up the Limelight
and staying keeping dirty with your
hands in the tech wnc was Steve Jobs
pocket
engineer
right and and frankly you know was
didn't want the Limelight he didn't want
to be doing all the thing telling people
making him other you know I I can
imagine was was and the people that were
on Steve Jobs Tech Team a lot of them
didn't get any of the credit Steve Jobs
though he got all the credit he got all
the credit and all these Engineers were
okay being the pocket Engineers for
Steve Jobs and making him look at it
they didn't care and they got paid they
got well they they you know they they
were very well renumerated why do you
care about all of this because you can
avoid manager suck you can avoid
becoming a manager and getting taken
away from the technology and the
engineering one of the ways to do that
is to stay really really good and the
way to get paid better is to make those
personal relationships with people who
are going to be judged based on how much
they know and they all know that their
skills are soft and the good ones the
ones that rise to the highest point to
you know the highest point in the CTO
and then they have a very elite team of
pocket engineers in the background
making them look good and if you're okay
with that you will do very well and you
will never have to be the face of of the
technologist if you want to be the face
and you're you're you're you're good
with social skills and you you you don't
necessarily want to have your hands dir
in the engineering that's another path
for you anyway uh us to growth at work
and I also hate it yeah absolutely
actually I one time people will try to
make your pocket engineer without even
doing it this is true story that
actually happened to me when I was at
Nike I sent around an architectural
document talking about the future of
where we needed to go and it set forth
some fiveyear plans sorts of things and
I sent it to a few isolated people
because I was the engineer I was the
engineer it wasn't appropriate for me to
spam the entire team right so I sent it
I sent it to two people I sent it to my
manager and I sent it to one of the
directors in technology and my manager
knew it and within a day this is a true
story within a day my manager brought me
in and she said you recognize this and
it was a letter it was an email it was
my exact email sent by this director who
had literally T taken his name off and
put my name on it and kept it verbatim
didn't even change a word I am not even
kidding that totally happened and I I
wish I could get bar to tell you how
that happened when she brought me in
that actually happened that's a sign
that you're good at what you do because
people were trying to plagiarize your
ideas and you had to be very careful
with that right because this guy wanted
want that happened another thing I did
the sort of the same thing online and an
entire internet service provider took
over my stuff and my manager at the time
she goes wait didn't you write this
document they yeah they just copi and
paste it our website and put it on their
website and put it under their name
happens all the time you're going to
have to fight this all the time and the
the only way to to do that is to to
create you know trusted relationships
and higher management because Barb saw
that my manager and then she immediately
said you know what are we going to do
about this and we confronted him we
confront him we both went to him and
said this isn't cool like why are you
doing that and he got like totally
reprimanded by upper management for that
and I my cred went through the roof on
that my cred went through the roof on
that because because now everybody knew
that this idea this guy's good idea had
actually come from me even though I was
just an
engineer so anyway that's that's how to
navigate the tech world and try to stay
actually one of the reasons that I
thought IBM was going to be the best
place for me to go is because there's
this there's another reality here that
you need to understand um there's only
so much money you can make for your Tech
skills even in Silicon valet at a
certain point if you want to make the
big big big big bucks you have to go to
management this is this is an
unfortunate reality Financial reality um
of the tech world and it sucks it
totally sucks you either have to and
that usually means that you have to like
make the technology or be a partner and
then sell your company all the people
that become Millionaires and it's a
totally different attack and there there
are twitch streamers and YouTubers who
will talk you know ad nauseum about how
to how to you know hack capitalism and
ride ride you know Silicon Valley all
the way to your millionaire status I'm
not interested in any of that
and and but one of the reasons I got
tempted by IBM was because IBM had a
title called distinguished engineer
which turns out to be total [__]
what it is I thought what I what I
thought it was was that IBM had figured
out a way to Renu re rumate as other
word to pay uh the the people who had
the tech skills and to keep them
increasing in income uh up to the
executive level so that that you know
that normal idea like okay I'm going to
be a technologist I have to cut over to
management okay it sucks to be a manager
but I'm making kickass money right that
you I I thought wrongly that you could
just continue the the tech path all the
way up to the top to the executive level
you cannot you absolutely cannot do that
at a certain point and this is true
everywhere at a certain point you have
to cut over to management you get soft
on your Tech skills and you got to hope
that the trajectory on management takes
you all the way to the Top If it doesn't
you're stuck in that very dangerous
place where you get eliminated and now
your Tech skills are soft and you don't
have the ability to turn around and get
another job because your Tech skills are
soft there you go avoid manager suck
that was a very long video but I feel
like it's an important one